"What Are the Best Foods?"
Instead of just looking at individual
studies, or individual reviews
of studies, what if you looked
at a review of reviews?
In my last video
I covered the beverages,
with the majority of reviews that
found some effects either way,
finding at least some benefits
to tea, coffee, wine, and milk
but not to sweetened
beverages such as soda.
As I explored in depth,
this approach isn't perfect.
It doesn't take into account
things like conflicts of interest
such as industry funding of studies
but can offer an interesting
bird's eye view on what's out
there in the medical literature.
What did the data show for food groups?
You'll note the first thing
the authors did was split it up
into plant-based foods
and animal foods.
For the broadest takeaway
we can look at the totals.
The vast majority of studies on whole
plant foods show either protective
or, at the very least, neutral effects,
whereas most reviews of animal-based
foods identified deleterious health
effects or, at best, neutral effects.
Let's break these down, though.
The plant-foods consistently rate
uniformly well, reflecting the total, but
the animal foods vary considerably.
As you can see, if it wasn't
for dairy and fish,
the animal foods total would swing
almost entirely neutral or negative.
I talked about the effects of dairy
industry funding in my last video,
as well as substitution effects.
Those who drink milk may be
less likely to drink soda,
a beverage even more
universally condemned,
so the protective effects
may be relative, arising
not necessarily from
what they're consuming
but rather from what they're avoiding.
This may best explain the fish findings.
After all, the prototypical choice
is between chicken and fish,
not chicken and chickpeas.
And not a single review found a single
protective effect of poultry consumption.
Even the soda industry could come
up with 14% protective effects,
but despite all the funding from
the National Chicken Council
and the American Egg Board, chicken
and eggs got big fat goose eggs.
Also, like the calcium in dairy,
there are healthful components of fish:
the long-chain omega-3 fatty acids.
Not for heart health. In the most
extensive systematic assessment
of effects of omega-3 fats on
cardiovascular health to date,
increasing the fish oil fats had little
or no effect on cardiovascular health.
In fact, if anything, it was
the plant-based omega-3s
found in flaxseeds and
walnuts that was protective.
But the long-chain omega-3s
are important for brain health.
Thankfully, just like there are
best-of-both-worlds non-dairy sources
of calcium, there are pollutant-free
sources of the long chain omega-3s,
EPA and DHA, as well.
The bottom line is that when it comes to
diet-related diseases such as obesity,
type 2 diabetes, mental health,
bone health, cardiovascular disease,
and cancers, even if you lump
all the animal foods together
and ignore any industry funding effects,
and just take the existing body of
evidence at face value, nine out
of ten study compilations show that
whole plant foods are, in the very least,
not bad, whereas about eight out of ten
of the reviews on animal products
show them to be not good.